Shri Ganesha is a giver of wisdom. He’s a giver
of wisdom, means just wisdom becomes a dharma,
becomes a part and parcel
of your being. You become just wise.
Now somebody may ask, “Mother how to become
wise?” It’s very difficult to say
how to become wise. It is just that it
happens that you become wise.
So, though He’s a child, He’s so matured.
He’s so wise. And He’s not only that,
but He emits wisdom. And this wisdom is an innate
quality of anyone who is a Sahaja Yogi.
Because in him, also, Shri Ganesha has been
awakened. So, he becomes a wise person,
very wise, and with wisdom what does he
achieve? He achieves a balance, a proper ascent
and also he understands that this ascent is
for his benevolence, for the benevolence of his country,
benevolence of the whole world. He
understands the importance of Sahaja Yoga.
Without this wisdom, one cannot understand.
And this wisdom is within us, just absolutely, innately built-in.
Only thing is, we have to
use the storehouse of this wisdom that is within us.
In that wisdom, you throw away whatever is wrong.
So, what a great work this Ganesha has to
do within ourselves!
This manifestation of Ganesha within us is very important, I think.
Not that it is only the basis, but also the foundation stone of spiritual
life is Shri Ganesha.
Once you are changed within, then you have full
idea as to what is expected of others,
what  they should do, what you are doing and how to
deal with them and how to talk to them, how to tell them,
how far to go with them –
everything. All this comes through wisdom.
In Sahaja Yoga, as you know, you are very
capable people, you have achieved a lot,
you know everything, you know all about chakras.
You  know practically everything. I
don’t hav to tell you anything.
Despite all that, one should have also the
wisdom how to deal with others, how to talk to others,
how to behave towards others, how not
to control anyone, not to say something that
will be rather harsh or hurting.
Because, if you are trying to spread Sahaja Yoga,
this is the only way we can go forward, is
to look after everyone with great compassion.
Now, we might think that wisdom is there
with us and we know how to do so many things
with our wisdom and now we are absolutely  wise. I agree, with Sahaja Yogis, now they have  become really very, very wise
and they know
how to use their wisdom.
But still, faith in themselves has to be really on a Nirvikalpa state.
That is only possible also with Shri Ganesha, because He is in Nirvikalpa.
So, in wisdom you don’t have to think,  argue.
I’ve seen many people who say, “Mother, you
see, we were thinking , then we had vibrations.
We didn’t know what to do, this, that,
how to do, how to correct, how to work it out”.
Now, I must say this is a state. It is not
a state to be achieved, but it’s a state.
Means you are there. It has to be innately built
in yourself, this state of wisdom.
But you can  also work it out by just concentrating on yourself
and trying to find out what’s the matter with me,
what happens to me, why,
why is it I’m like this.
The introspection can help you a lot to be extremely wise, but easier method is to worship
the principle of innocence within yourself.
So, the first thing is live in the present.
The wisdom is in living in the present. Present, we are here, so forget the past.
Now, if I say,  “Forget the past”, one may say, “How to do it?
How to forget the past?”
Again, I would say, meditation is the only way. You give up your left and you give up your right and you are just standing in the centre,
enjoying the wisdom, enjoying the joy of your being.
So, this wisdom is to live in the present,
This is a very good practice. One has to
practice wisdom through living in the present.
That’s how you can really establish yourself in
wisdom, itself, means the wisdom acts by itself.
It’s a power. Wisdom is a very big power. If
you are a wise person, it’s a power.
It can combat any kind of ignorance, any kind of
attacks, any kind of stupidity.
It’s such a tremendous power that God has given us, that
we are wise. And this wisdom, you should try to really,
to develop it and mature it properly within ourselves.
So, today’s Shri Ganesha’s Puja is there, while  we should ask for wisdom. And for that, we have to be in the present.
Every way you should be in the present.
Now all these qualities described, of the Devi
[that] are left sided, are in the brain: memory,
‘smruti rupena sansthita’. Other things also
– whatever are described – are in the brain.
And then the bhakti reaches the stage [where] it just neutralises everything.
All the problems of the brain are neutralised
and you become a wise person. So the greatest boon of the Devi is to give you wisdom.
You can call  it awareness, you can call it anything,
but it’s a kind of a wisdom by which
you become absolutely a Divine personality.
That wisdom you must reach through your bhakti.
It should not be blind, it should not be blind,
but it should be wise bhakti, wise with wisdom.
Only possible through Sahaja Yoga, I think,
otherwise, whatever bhakti people do like mad,
that cannot be bhakti.
So many complaints come to me, about Sahaja
Yogis also. I am surprised, why: why are they doing like that?
I would say, still,
they have not reached the state of bhakti.
We get into diseases and we are trapped into
all kinds of things; it is because we don’t have bhakti.
In the bhakti, you have to depend
on the wisdom of the Mother, wisdom of the Shakti,
that She looks after you, She finds you out the way and She will help you.
Now first test your wisdom, you must test your
wisdom, “If I am doing this, is this wise, is it good,
why I am doing it?” First test your wisdom, then you’ll find out that many things you do which are wrong,
which should not have been done.
But first your wisdom must develop and you
must see that your wisdom works and helps you.
If you  cannot find out what is good and what is
bad that means the wisdom is lacking.
If you cannot find out what should you
do then the wisdom is lacking.
But, if you have the wisdom, then you
will immediately know that this is wrong.
And the wisdom is the thing which really is not
just assumption that, “I am very wise and all that,”
but it asserts, it works out and
it shows what is good and what is bad.
Wisdom is the sign of a person who is really a
realised soul of a very high level.
If you don’t have wisdom whatever you may do, you might
feel satisfied about it,
but the wisdom part is very, very important.
That is the most governing part within us
and as you know, Ganesha is the giver of wisdom.
That’s why Ganesha must be worshipped.
With a proper upbringing Shri Ganesha is
established, who is nothing but the giver of wisdom.
And this wisdom is innate. You don’t
have to judge it, it’s innate within us,
grown up, just like any other qualities in us.
It takes time with some people,
it takes time,  no doubt. But once it comes in, such a person
becomes quiet, simple and absolutely truthful.
He knows about everything. And this is the
thing one should develop is, “How far am I wise?”
He’s not worried about his financial side,
or emotional side, nothing! What he is worried is,
“Have I been a wise person?”
That is the first sign of the blessings of God.
The one who has blessings of Divine is a wise person,
he’s very wise and his wisdom is
shown by his silence.
we have developed this wisdom
within us, through what?
Through our meditation, through our
understanding of bhakti and shraddha.
So it’s very important to understand
the value of bhakti within us.
You cannot superficially touch it. Those who
are superficial will never get it.
Wisdom only comes through understanding what is wisdom is.
So the Sahaj Yogi is the one who has to have
that wisdom, “Why I am doing this? What is the need to do it?”
They don’t have to ask any questions, they just don’t do wrong things. They just don’t do wrong things.
They are always on the right path. That is the sign of a Sahaj Yogi, I believe,
and which is the blessing  of the Goddess. If there is the Power of the Goddess working in you,
you will  have the wisdom to work it out.
For a person who is standing in his wisdom, is
the sage as they call him, is the saint as they call it.
But, this can be every Sahaja Yogi could be a saint, could be a sage, every Sahaja Yogi could be that.
But if you lose
your wisdom then you are no good.
So, I have to tell you one thing:
it’s your wisdom which will save you.
Your wisdom will
unconsciously help you.
there are many incidents people have told
me, that, “Mother, how we were saved,
how we were brought to the brink of death
and then how we are just alive.”
It is because the Divine needs you, Divine doesn’t
want you to die, or to finish off, it needs you very much.
It has to do its work and you
are the instrument of that Divine.
If you have wisdom you are the best instrument
for the Divine to work it out.
you should try to find out – are you wise
enough? Are you wise, or are you not?
It’s very difficult for every human being to
find out whether you are right or wrong
because you see the effects of this wisdom all around.
So, the bhakti and shraddha to the Goddess gives you,
definitely gives you, wisdom. We
have had some people in India who did  lots of bhakti, so called,
and showed lots of
shraddha, but they were not, they were not.
Just they were talking about it, or doing all
kinds of things about it but they were not.
So wisdom is something a very innate
quality, very innate, it’s not superficial.
You cannot just say that
this person is wise or not.
It shows, that’s just like a power, it’s a
power of understanding and is supported by the Power of the Goddess.
So She is the giver of wisdom. This is the biggest quality of the Goddess,
that She is the giver of wisdom. And wisdom comes as a part of the evolutionary process.
Now She has brought about all the evolution so far,
and to go further She is going to make you a very wise person.
First of all you must follow only thing that is
real, not unreal things. For that also, again, you need wisdom.
I think for that you need
wisdom very much more. And that is something,
whether you have the wisdom first, or you have
the blessings of the Mother, is between the two.
So I have to tell you one thing that: before
you people start spreading Sahaja Yoga,
please judge yourself. Just see if you are wise enough.
Also see for yourself if you have the blessings of the Mother.
Only the wise are, I should say,  the people who know whether they have the Mother’s blessings or not.
For that we have so many ways of understanding.
First and foremost thing is meditation
and feeling your vibrations on the photograph and
facing yourself clearly.
If you are a realised soul, are you really a
good realised soul or not? Are you deep or not?
Are your vibrations working out or not?
If you can see that then you will realise that
greater than all ambitions, the greatest is to
become a devoted, wise personality.
But, on the whole, what I feel is you can
support me very much, you can support my work very much,
if you have that wisdom.
And the wisdom is to judge yourself:
how many people you love? How you love?
How you talk to them? What do you want out of them?
All this should come.
Judge yourself – introspection.
Through introspection you can see it.
So, for a Sahaja Yogi is important is  introspection.
Second one is meditation.
And third one is to take vibrations. It’s very important.
The first thing is that if you want your Gurupad,  you have to be innocent. “Innocent” is a very vague term, very vague,
and it’s difficult to really understand what is innocent.
But what is the nature of innocence? That we can understand
from Shri Ganesha’s innocence. First of
all, He’s endowed with wisdom, and He puts wisdom into us.
It’s a nice thing now in modern times we have discovered genetics, and genetics determine our behaviour and our races.
It is He who puts genetics in us. He selects and  puts it within us, our genetics,
and when He puts wisdom in us, then we are wise.
There is definitely a genetic of wisdom which  is lacking, as we can see very clearly, in many races. They have no wisdom.
They do things without wisdom. They do things just for their destruction, destroying their society.
They may call themselves the highest society, highest races,
whatever it is – you may brand yourself with anything – but you can see from their behaviour
that they have no wisdom at all.
So He’s the one who puts that wisdom in us.
In some people who are not yet evolved – certain
races are not yet evolved to that extent – this wisdom is lacking.
Apart from that, this
wisdom gives us the sense of freedom.
So we keep aloof from all kinds of intoxicants, all
kinds of bad habits. We don’t like to look at nudity.
It can never become the lifestyle
of people who have wisdom. Never.
We don’t indulge into extramarital nonsense. Whatever
is absolutely in the centre, which is dharmic,
we accept. So we can see that the seed of wisdom put into us makes us dharmic people
when we grow, automatically. We are automatically dharmic.
This wisdom comes to you through Shri Ganesh.
In short, He makes you absolutely ready for Self-Realization.
So this wisdom is innate. It just happens
that when the Kundalini is rising, He becomes
manifesting in us – I should say, He makes us  like a child.
And that’s what Christ has said, that you have to be like children if you have to enter into the Kingdom of God.
You become
the child, at that time you become a child.
And with the Kundalini rising, that wisdom then
comes into your brain, because He’s sitting on the Kundalini itself.
He’s the power in the
Kundalini. He gives wisdom in the brain.
Once you get that wisdom, you drop out all
bad habits. All your attachments which are wrong,
all adharmic things that you do, everything
drops out. He changes, your genetics are changed.
The genetics of Sahaja Yogis are
that all of them will be the same. About the same, I would say.
And the genetics
of other people would be different.
A child who has wisdom is extremely cautious,
he understands the importance of his life.
He respects his parents, he respects everything
– automatically. You don’t have to tell them.
Automatically they know what
dharma is, you don’t have to tell them.
That wisdom, this great deity of Ganesha gives you. He took His form as Jesus Christ.
And you all accepted Him as the Lord, which is
true also. But because your Ganesh principle
was not so much developed in these Western
countries, people took to stupid things.
As soon as you get wisdom, you
understand holiness and auspiciousness.
So this wisdom part is so important, and
that’s what we should ask Ganesha: to make us like children.
Children have basically wisdom,
but not all the children. This is the thing,
that children in which Shri Ganesha has
activated, has put this genetic of wisdom, it is there.
This is one of the greatest things we have
to think about: is it wise, it is sane? It’s not to be logically;
logically if you believe in  something, then you can go wrong because there’s no strength from within.
But innately if it becomes that, you won’t do it at any cost.
I mean, for today, as it is we had to delay, and
I’ve tried to give you some points about Shri Ganesh.
I think even if you give Me a hundred
lectures I cannot finish it, it’s so great.
It’s like an ocean to Me. So I hope
you will understand the essential,
the fundamental principles
of Shri Ganesha, and what innocence is.
The first is wisdom.
May God bless you all.